hi all good evening guys am i audible and visible
guys can you hear me out
good evening all let me share my screen too
hello rajni so screen share is also working fine guys
so I hope everyone is you know doing their assignment problems and you know
keeping up with right amount of PSP's and prepping for the mock too many
things are going to come up next week because next weekend I guess you have a
mock like contest for the whole HTMLC as a JS part so irrespective of any
frameworks guys these are going to play really important you know the whatever
topics we have covered whatever concepts we have covered from day in till today
are most important I would request right everyone to keep revising the go
through the github and it's that's more important related to certification
contest is it about mock interview Ashish are you talking about that once
you do a mock interview you'll be able to get a certification isn't it
certification contest let me check on this hi okay I'll talk about that on
used I have to gather complete knowledge on that yeah because I okay
Muneshwara says that is for DSA technical certification test okay that
might be DSA test is it only for practice so I hope Ashish your question
was actually answered by Muneshwara github link sure just a second
I have attached here in the chat history great so how's your weekend going
us guys how's the weekend going are you prepping continuously or there's
something happening spy stuff news are you applying it any forms I know many of
the many of you have told me that after react will start applying I but as you
know there is a lot of calls from HRS of different organizations I think she
nice so you are in Hyderabad itself right Muneshwara
I'll type anglo okay so we'll wait for some time till people join classes class
so then we'll get started let me bring in chart
maybe we can plan make for this batch if possible or got clemency I sure sure
I'll sometime visit Bangalore maybe this month and itself my sister stays there
so they moved out to Bangalore so I'll probably coming there electronic city
maybe they stay there guys did anyone understand the picture that I have a
send in whatsapp chat like whatsapp group chat yeah we can meet but did anyone saw
that picture CSR SSR CSR plus SSR did you guys just understood that point like
anyone just did they understand anything on that part no no but that's
one of the architectural discussions architectural decisions like but I'll
talk about that in future class but just wanted to know if anyone have the
context on that already because it's a really big topic to discuss once
complete once we complete react then we'll talk on that part how things are
working how completely things are rendered let me see one document this
was the article that you have to
good guys I'll urge everyone to go through this article after the class or
anytime you find time but you know you should be knowing each and everything
like how three things combined firstly how things are built like how Dom is
built behind the scenes how CSS is actually mapped to each of the HTML
node in that Dom key then how JS is actually downloaded and you know mixed
and rendered with them how things works coordinate okay so I hope everyone goes
through this article in a break or post class but in case you have any doubts
bring it up with me in the next class I will discuss that in further okay spend
some time understanding how complete rendering works because most of the the
concepts that that I've shared picture right CSR SSR plus CSR plus SSR all
these things will make sense only once you know how rendering works now when I
talk about rendering how HTML CSS and JS are actually loaded and works in
browser because we know that there is something called Dom tree but you also
have something like Sysarm Sysarm is for CSS tree then Dom tree then you have
mix both the things then you build something called as a render tree now
this render tree is actually rendered in the browser so before actually you know
working with anything once your HTML and CSS are downloaded in the network they
build these two data structures of Dom and Syscom then they merge to build
something called render tree then it works finally you also have JS and we
have seen that how JS get downloaded you have async keyword then you have differ
keyword then you don't do it anything then you know how it works so
combinations of these things is actually how you should be understanding this how
browser is handling all the edge cases once you know this maybe then we'll talk
on this completely like sometime later of once we cover that yet because this
is like specifically architectural decisions like how do you build certain
components of the apps what's the best strategy okay this is really
important from a senior a depth point of view I found that interesting I found
it that in LinkedIn so I've just shared it but I but the whatever article have
shared with you please understand those those will covered about this for this
part and this part and this one and this thing we have anyways covered how JS
okay and then we'll get started but I hope everyone you know find some time
five minutes they can keep that open in the tab in your machine so that you will
find time anyways go through that article because this will build your
basics from rendering point of view because the JavaScript HTML CSS I'll
teach it I'll teach up to an extent behind the scenes how things works but
there might be some parts where I'll share the documentation or things where
you have to put in efforts but in case you don't understand anything going
through the commit documentation I'll be there to help you out okay I see less
amount of people Saturday but what should we do guys it's ten minutes
already should we get started I see only one thumbs up few more guys few more
thumbs up so nice but yeah thank you guys so just wanted to know like did you
understand what polyfills are and how can you write polyfills for HOF that we
have discussed in last class could be filter could be map for each and we also
consider reduce and flat these are the all methods which are built on array
like these are the utility methods there can be a number of utility methods you
might be writing in your project that we have just rewritten the logics how those
things should work right now once this part is clear like we have further three
things to rediscuss and reimplement it which are call bind apply polyfills for
them we have discussed the concept for this one but just want to know if you
remember the concept for this one guys can anyone summarize the concept for
this one do you remember guys call bind apply when when we actually use this
method three methods when does when what is your use case like why do we
actually use this three methods if you don't remember it give me thumbs down if
you remember it trying to put it in sentence give a thumbs up okay I see five
people don't remember it okay so as you remember that we use this method to
of this while borrowing function like we were actually changing what this should
be pointing to we were specifically passing an object and we say that hey
this should point to this particular object we were making sure that and all
of them were doing the same things but everyone was behaving in a different way
we know that call takes a list of arguments whereas apply takes an array
of arguments extra arguments whereas bind used to return a function which can
be called a number of times are we able to recall this with this short
introduction again because I'll build those examples one by one and we'll
write polyfills for them once we cover this polyfills will have some
interesting you know JS sort of revision concepts but want to discuss about few
of the you know basics that you have to work on okay so we'll have some of the
more of conversational things going on today after this polyfills will cover
them in half an hour I don't think it would need more time but next one one
eight of our class would be much interesting okay let's let's go back to
this one so can I get started with call bind apply or do you want me to re
explain this topic guys because this was covered in earlier class there was a
specific amount of time was given to this class on call by bind apply we have
spent more than an hour right continue right okay let's not waste the time and
focus on this so one of the one one example I'll pick it up so that everyone
can recall it let's say I'll build one file polyfill call bind apply not JS
let's say this is one of the file that I have and let's say we you know doing it
again now if you say that I have a simple I'll take the same example person
object and object will have again let's say name and age say name and age okay
let's keep it name itself make it further simple and let's say you also
have let's make this const you have another const percent two you have name
again let's say we call it as a myth right then we had some common function
let's say a function of separate age where it's I receive an age but when I
try to do a console dot log I'll say that this start name is years old let's
say years old now this was a use case when we wanted to use call bind apply
let's say I'm using an example of call what I can do is that since I just need
to call it what first thing is that something always I used to call it on an
object let's say firstly I call it as this print age function now on this
print age always when I'm borrowing this function I can apply three methods on it
call blind apply I'll call this one then I can pass what this should point to I'll
say that this should point to person object and then also can pass an age
because we are accepting an age in this print age right so this is how we have
learned it now let's see if this is working fine node so I hope this is
something how it is working I hope everyone knows it one final thumbs up if
you can further recall this one better right like why this is working this way
and how this is this generally if you remember what this should be pointing to
in a normal function what this is usually points to can you guys remember
that one what they should point to it's a node.js non-strict environment it
should point to an empty object isn't it this is the example this is sorry this
inside a function it should point to a global object isn't it like this inside
a function so I hope you remember these differences all the things that we have
covered now we change that one from window object to this person object now
just let's think like how can we approach now a polyfill for this one like
where we are changing a context for this one we have covered this one in one of
the class where we were discussing in doubt session but I made a pretty much
simple code now but just want to just want you to think like what is actually
this thing is doing this is just changing what this is pointing to isn't
it nothing else and we are passing that inside this function how would you
approach this one
so I want to call this one as a printage dot my call person 2 and 23 let's say
this should print Amit is years of 23 years old so this is something like my
call function we have to build it but how would you approach this one guys
what we have discussed in last class firstly this should be available on
which library like which part of this my call should be available on what is the
data type of this parentage function isn't it so let's slide down that
syntax step by step okay function dot prototype dot my call once we have this
then there is a function okay inside this function there's something happening
but inside this function on my call what we are taking it they shall just wait
talked about like how call works call wind apply and then we started with a
prototype of call nothing much okay so if you remember if you see it here my
call is actually taking two parameters one is object and the other one is the
edge so let's say we say that this is a context object where we are changing new
context and also we can say that we have a list of arguments okay now what I'll
do here is that firstly I'll check that if context is undefined then I'll say
put context equal to this one a check normal check but later on you have to
you guys have to explain me what this would be pointing out here if you if you
crack this what this is pointing here everything will be clear is it context
that's that's coming out of you know autocomplete but think from a concept
point of view neshara if you remember in last class if you remember in last class
when we covered for each or anything this was pointing to add a right
because we were calling added or for each this was pointing to an array same
way here this should be actually pointing to
function itself right yes are you able to link that point why this like let me
try to console log this here you see when I'm trying to console log this
actually I'm getting a print age function okay now I have this function I
have to call this function in a such a way that I have to change the context of
this one and with value 23 how can I do it how can I make sure that like this is
actually pointing to my current object and you can always you know or try to
open in a new tab this particular box you you will be able to see that this is
a third is a use case like if you see third number this object function what
we are saying I mean this inside an object which is it again there is a
function inside a function so we are returning object itself this is the use
case that we have to replicate it isn't it like there is an object inside that
we have function inside that we are having a disk keyword what I exactly
meant to meant by this is that if you can build something let's say a const
object where you have let's say let's say some function funk pointing this
then also if you remember in the context anyways we have all the things if I
spread context this way do you think the no inside this context anyways
whatever when I try to refer here inside the function I'll be able to get that
values right whatever is needed like this is same way this is same way as
let's say I have OBJ 2 I say name John age 42 let's say print age okay let's
remove this arrow function convert into function okay and console dot log of
this start name is years old even if I do this start age or if I pass an age
here how can I call this I can make a call like OBJ 2 dot print age and pass
on some age this should work right if we are able to replicate this one inside
here the work should be done isn't it because we know that whenever we are
making a call this way it the this is particularly pointing to object itself
and inside that you have this dot name and age available so stocking but this
like you if you can replicate this particular functionality of this third
key your job will be done so how many of you are able to connect this dots there
are people trying you know facing challenge and understanding this one give
me thumbs down okay I see one person who don't understand two people three
just let me see okay so firstly promote Kabir so are you able to recall this
example firstly this this sort of use case that what this will be pointing
here firstly all of you all of you three guys like this example right how we made
sure that you know this object should be this object should be actually
pointing to this if I remove this function outside if I remove this
function outside and I try to say that trying to print this we know this
example that it will be pointing to a global object right if I remove this
function out of it like if I am able to pull this out this will point into global
object isn't it and what I'm saying is that convert this use case convert this
use case into this use case from second to third which will fix our polyfill
okay because because we are already having this function here this and this
is already pointing to window this is already pointing to window now I should
make sure in a way inside this prototype prototype dot my call to build a function
of like this way since I have all the variables needed here because if you
see in the context if you see the context we are passing that object we
have all the information needed like name and everything is available also I
have H and inside of this keyword also I'm having a function so can't I
replicate this use case so I hope approach approach is clear like how we
are actually thinking like how we can build this one let me say that if I say
that let's say I have one more check one more check is that firstly I'll check
like if type of this is not equal to function then I'll return throw error
can be called only on function okay now once I have this now let's say if I'm
actually if you see this this is an object that I'm having right can I do
something like adding a new property I say that object dot let's say function
new function which I want to add what this single sentence has done it what
this particular single sentence has done it this particular single sentence has
changed if you see this use case if I try to remove all of them now if you
remember if you want to add a new property into an object this is the one
way of doing it or else you can always write down context start funk once we
write this I added a new property and this is actually pointing to an object
now inside this context currently what what else what we have we have name can
be any name whatever we pass in the context also I created a funk and here
I have something like print age now when I do this use case once I do this use
case my problem is solved isn't it I can call this function directly guys are
you able to relate this one again I see only one thumbs up if I need few more to
understand whether you are able to follow up or not I'll show you in the
debugging mode once more let's say once I make this I've added a new thing into
this one I have to just call this funk right once I have to call this funk with
all the arguments that I have
I'm just calling this funk and what else you can do you need not to return
anything because this is not returning anything it is just executing with
changing the context now let's say if this is working fine I'll comment this
part I'll remove this part let me show you step by step
so have you guys tried debugging in JS like both browser and VS code have
taught you how to do it right so I hope everyone is doing it now guys if you see
it what just happened here what we have done it just in order to implement my
call as I've told you that firstly this is inside this we have this function
print age is coming because we are calling print age that my call always
this will be pointing to plug-in I don't we don't really need plug-in
muneshwara we can directly do it I'll talk about that but let's focus on this
example again guys that if you see here when I try to print this if I see if I
console log here this you will see this I'm getting print age function because
we are calling print age here once now if I do like context dot now let's see
if I execute this part of line and I move to next line now what happens in
the context as I've told you that earlier that a new key is created inside
the object called funk and print age is applied and this is somehow we converted
into this use case isn't it third line so once we've done this we know that
always in this use case if I call a function like this one like context dot
funk we note that this will be pointing to the context itself you know that is
the reason why we we tell that you know you should revise this or you should
revise all the things so that you'll have a better clarity now I'm passing the
arcs which will actually is similar to the age 23 whatever I'm receiving here
I'm passing that and just executing it now this once we execute it let's see
output now if you see I got Amit is 23 years old because percent two having the
Amit name in it so let me know guys if there is still anyone who don't
understand this one if there is anyone who don't understand this one please let
me know I'll try to repeat it again if this thing is clear can give me
thumbs up once this thing is clear can you give me thumbs up once I see three
people further I have more than 25 people guys can you give me some you
know reactions so that I understand that whether should I move forward or not
okay I see four people okay I hope you are able to follow up I received eight
people routine 50% of not even 50% of class but it's okay I hope but everyone
is able to follow up and able to understand this concept like how we are
building up in a polyfill for call now there is a only small change we know
that if you want to call it for apply let's say if I again on a same function
if I want to call and apply same thing I can do is that I can say a percent or
two and I have to pass arguments in an array isn't it this is the only
difference isn't it in call and apply do you guys remember this right now let's
say that if I want to build a polyfill for this one what will be a small change
that we have to address it what will be a small change we have to address it
here inside this if I let's say if I copy this and let's say I paste it here I say
that my apply what I should be doing it here on this only on the list of
arguments what I have to do it
take array instead of box okay let's say I have an array no once I have an array
again I can I'll have to destructure here right I have to spread it I have to
spread those items isn't it I can say something here is that if type of ARR
is not equal equal to can I say that our array then throw a new array
Kabir for call and apply so I didn't get it like what comments you need it how
this is working because this concepts we have discussed earlier in the class
right that's why I'm not focusing on the concept but on a polyfill more
guys do you want me to okay okay let's say I have a divider here firstly
okay yeah no worries but guys is there anything else like I have to do it
specifically for handling apply from logical point of view because they're
still doing that same thing isn't it on my apply it's just that we are receiving
an array and anyways if I want to execute that item function again I have
to destructure them and pass it on isn't it are you are you able to recall like
how apply used to work let's say I try to show it taking the same set example
I recall person one and instead of this I'll say my apply let's say we re-execute
this one I'll remove debuggers from here okay I got an error
okay person one was a person is not a person one object no okay say what is
a type of it's an object like say clear this again re-executing this one okay
we are still going inside this so let me write this again not equal equal to
object so you cannot actually compare so single string but the other capital O is
a mistake let's play this one re-execute this one okay now guys the only difference
we had with call and apply was like the way the extra arguments are being passed as we
have discussed earlier also in the class that you know doesn't really matter if you use
call and apply today's age because you have destructuring syntax where you can extract
and spread you know spread up you can use the spread operator where you can spread all the
arguments that you are getting in an array isn't it still that same syntax and just whatever you
are receiving here if you see array is having an item with the zero at the index 23 which I'm
spreading it now depending upon how the function is accepting parameters it will be the same if you
want manually you can do it here manually but this is how you should be building it and this
would be working fine for the interviews okay this is this point here what's the basic difference
funda here between my apply and my call the both are same in a way behind the scenes right let
me add a comment here okay then we have pretty much simple implementation again we have bind
if you remember bind also it used to return a function for us isn't it let's say return
function I call this as this one and if I call print my age dot bind and I pass the object and
again it takes any are any way of elements defined let's say I pass again 32 let's see
what we get in return if I try to console dot log return function firstly now if you see I'm
getting a bounded a print age now that bounded print age is like if you try to execute this part
again it will work like a same my call apply where context is changed and you get the way
you want it so you remember this how bind works bind used to return a function after changing the
context and whenever you want to execute this function anywhere you can always execute this
depending upon your use case it's still doing the same part where it's changing the context
of this inside it as do you remember bind I kept asking like do you remember do you remember but
I'm not sure like if you are able to recall those examples like what we have picked it up but these
are pretty straightforward so that's the reason why I'm moving in bit speed again if I have to
build a prototype on this one let's say I call function dot prototype dot my bind and if you
see I have a function against like let's say this is a function and where you receive two things
and context object and least of arguments once you have this one check you can do is this one
if I write down the same logic what is the one thing that I should be doing it here what is the
one difference I should be doing it here can you guys think what is the one common difference that
my bind does it return some function isn't it it returns your function it returns you some function
do you agree with that point it is returning some function and what that function usually do it once
it is returned let's say this you call this function whatever you are returning here once
this function is received when you call this there is something executed inside it there is
something which is executed inside it now the way you can always execute is like again if I try to
rewrite this line here this is it right now if you remember if I call somewhere my bind I'm call
returning a function and if I execute this particular function this one this will be
executed automatically with the least of arguments I what I will do is that guys is that I'll repeat
it again all of this thing so that you remember this okay there's a one tweak you can always do
it but before that let me show you that this works fine so I call it as one if you see I've
got again a bounded vintage still we are getting that same output with our instead of this one
let's say I call my bind I shouldn't be calling on library itself okay got an error okay let's
add it here once you have it you will be able to pass on the information now what is one thing
here we have to address it what do you guys think that why my aux is not being actually declared
but values okay let's say I pass on my aux here I was not reading it properly so it is working
fine but there's a small tweak tweak that you can always do is that let's say you passed on
information this way that's all fine it is returning your function and this function is
actually being returned what if we can pass our parameters to this one also like what if I can
say that I can pass some parameter like let's say random string something like how would you
accept this parameter you can also accept arguments here once this is returned and you
can what you can do is like you can always merge here a list of arguments okay whenever
you are returning let's say if you want to pass like this information let's go to this
I'll also since we are accepting age only here let's say one string something we are
receiving here let's say if I try to console dot log of string you will be able to see that that
is being outputted in all other cases you will get an undefined because we are not passing
something extra if I re-execute this one if you see every place I got undefined because we're
not passing there but here we pass something like random where the extra parameter was
passed inside the return function guys are you able to connect with connect the dots with this
one like what my call my bind how these things are working just want to I don't think that you
got the confidence on this is it isn't it I see only a few people reacting it so just want to
know that we are able to understand this one or not give me honest response guys like did
you understand this concept of poly full of call by apply buying need to revise so let me give you
you know just off it again so on the iPad you know as I've told you that firstly all of these
things were only changing the context of this this might be our sub you know in order to you
know rewrite your own libraries poly fields okay so in that interviews they might ask it but not
in real time like you would be doing it in development purposes mostly because you use
latest process itself as I have introduced when I introduced a poly fields I talked about that
like how would you do it and why would you do it okay but just let me let me share like what's
actually happening if you see we had two objects like person one and name some random string and
person to object of name and we had print age function which was taking age and trying to
print this not name and let's say and age let's say we are printing this one now we know that
whenever we call in a node.js non-strict environment in a simple function this points to global object
so if I pass on something let's say for pass on I call directly person let's say if I call
print age passing 23 it will give me undefined and 23 right so this was something that we already
know that how this would work right now what was our role was that hey this undefined shouldn't
be actually undefined this is something should be all anyways is with this object so what I've told
is that for the all the functions right all the functions prototype I'll build some method like
my call and that my method call will take two parameters one is this object itself called
person one and age now the call would become actually my call dot person one and 23 but once
I have this what I was actually doing here is that if you see this object right whenever person
one object this person one is having what I was doing is that person one dot new function and
that function I was attaching to this because if you remember I call always my call on this
print age function itself the call was actually print age dot my call and I was doing it this
when I do this this will be actually available in this function so after doing this what happened
here inside this object a new func key was added and we had the whole function available inside it
now once that was available the next step was only calling this function person one dot func we know
that in order to call from object you can always call this way and I can pass age this was my call
isn't it I've just changed how you remember how how the this is actually pointing to when I
converted it this way you always know that if I write down this inside this one and this name
is available here so this dot name will always return me the name instead of anything else
instead of global object right this I see only one reaction but did you get that context did
you understood like how the concept how we are changing it just like if you you can always go
to that image that we have applied because this poly fields right for call by and apply
test your knowledge like how this is working and how would you convert from one format to the other
format here just we are converting from yeah today's class is challenging because this again
I'm asking you to recall the other concept and how would you convert from the you know objects
like how that pointing to this is changing that's the reason why we took whole one class spending
time on this one understanding yeah but do one thing I would request everyone after the class
right put the debuggers on try to convert it what I'll do it is that I'll have add some comments
on this so that you guys remember it now here let's say till this point I'll add comments for
one part context object is actually having one thing name John okay and this is actually
available function print age so what I did I created for context equal to name John and funk
print age okay I have created object this way how did I was able to do this like I call I just
said that this line when I say this line this was actually done okay let me write down the top now
we know that in an example whenever you try to get at this inside out of this context like when
I call this way context dot funk execute it whatever I pass here age or anything but this
name is available here so this dot name is always working so there's only one example which we tweak
something to build all of this because all of them were seen okay guys one final reactions
guys so that we can move ahead because there are too many bounces coming up now you have to face
too many things today okay now I'll build an file called example.js just example.js file nothing
else here let's say I have a few list of questions I want you to expect or answer me what could be
the output of this one okay let's say if I try to do console dot of X okay what could be the output
here if I just do this console dot of X directly what can be the output rethink it okay Arun and
Ashish says that undefined Kabir says that X anyone else having any other Ashish again says
X changes answer Muneshwara says X okay undeclared so what was undeclared Dheeraj what used to say
that we had two keywords undefined and not defined what should be the output here so rethink it guys
you know like what should be the like what do you think like whether it should be X are not
defined or undefined actually testing your whole knowledge right refining whole things that we have
learned to throughout chase so how many of you think it should be if you think undefined give
me thumbs up if you think it's not defined give me thumbs down I see save seven people eight all
people are saying not defined okay great so firstly I want to put one thing is that it doesn't print
X because X is not a string here if I added a string format it would have printed X that point
is clear it wouldn't print X the reason is that it is not a string it is a value it is trying to
refer to something it's a variable value and this variable X is not defined isn't it let's to show
you guys what I will do is that after every question I'll try to print it here in the console
let's say I refresh it I try to print it you see that X is not defined is an error I hope everyone
got it right and confident about this one so sometimes in interviews they might trick you
this way now let's say second question is I have Y equal to one console dot of Y I say that where Y
just think of this context what could be the answer here Dheeraj says one
and if you think one why would you think it should be one what is the reason behind it
muneshwara says not defined hoisting
okay where key hoisting global so if how many of you think that if it is a one give me thumbs
up guys if you think there is some other thing give me thumbs down
okay I have three people who say it's not one okay just a second muneshwara pradeep shashank says not
one hoisting concept so how many of you remember execution context and hoisting concept guys
now what usually happen with hoisting what usually happen with the hoisting what generally it says
that all the variables yeah let and const are in temporal zone dead zone but all the variables
which are with var and functions are generally hoisted or declared but not initialized right
all the variables in the file all the variables and functions are declared okay but not
initialized here when I when I try to load a file when I try to load the file
var y is there it will skim through it it will it will create or declare this variable y right
on through the top this will be actually converted at real time let's say if I write down at real
time this will be converted as like var y then y equal to one then console dot log of y this
will be converted into reverse order do you guys agree with this my point
how this will be actually done in behind the scenes
okay let's see this let's see this output uh okay
if I try to print it now do you see this one is coming out
okay I hope you are able to follow up why this thing has actually happened in question two
and then I'll put up another question let's say I try to console dot log
or let's say z and let's say I give var z equal to one what should be the value of this one
uh
theory says undefined uh kabir uh kabir what's your question it's one okay uh promote says one
muneshwara says one
um
so if you if you guys think answer should be one can you give me thumbs up and if you think
undefined can you give me thumbs down
rajnees is not defined
okay uh so there's a complete split but let me ask you one question difference between
declaration and initialization
people whoever gave me one I just want to ask the difference between declaration and initialization
how behind the scenes in hosting used to work is that if you remember whenever this logic is done
you will be initializing where's that then you still have console dot log z
okay then you have z equal to one this was converted into this way and at this point
z is undefined we know that first time when the things are wasted it holds a value of undefined
okay right so people who have gave me uh for one right do you understand this
kabir muneshwara pramod why did one is wrong here
let me show you here executing in the browser again let me copy this I clean it up I paste it
here okay do you see this undefined coming out okay so firstly when I say this step is called
declaration I declared a variable called z but I didn't put a value called one in it yet
when I'm hosting the value the declaration happens value is not assigned the default
value which is assigned is undefined for the variables
okay so when I'm trying to print it here I'll get an undefined because at the line number 19
actual value is being supplied okay so this will output in undefined
are these three questions clear clear guys what is why behind the scenes and what the things are
going on for these three questions is there anyone who is having any doubts in this
okay now let's say if I go with a question for
let's say I have a equal to one
one then if I try to do console log a
I I do something let a this one what do you think output should be now
so
okay mixed answers undefined error one
okay
firstly is this line valid
is this line valid
okay no
okay let's let's check this like actually firstly because in the let first we have to declare then
initialize what was your answer you said error right now right
how let and const used to work there is a basic difference between where let and const when it
comes to hoisting concept because let and const actually fixed hoisting issues isn't it
now let me show you the output firstly what it would be there you clean it up
I throw it you see cannot access a before initialization it says
this when I'm trying to console log we say that a is not initialized if I convert this itself if
I convert this into where this is fixed okay because this memory is loaded already if I clean
it up reload the browser if I give it up here I'll be able to print it but if I try to
just change from where to let there is a change in hoisting concept there is something like
temporal dead zone in temporal dead zone this doesn't really you know hoisted to the global
space they are actually hoisted to their local space in that use cases it is it works as expected
guys read as it is when it comes to let and const okay you have to declare it then initialize
it when it comes to let and const because we are fixing that random behavior which is happening
is this point here like why we are getting here error because we haven't first we have to declare
then initialize then go on okay that's a basic difference that has happened I'll put it as an
error here let's say I have another question five
now simple thing console dot log b let's say I have let b equal to one now what do you think
I've just I've just told you that when it comes to let and const read as it as it is through
read as it as it is
like is it be accessible first guys is it be accessible first does b exist
right if if it would have been here below that would be good that's the reason why I'm saying
that hey consider it there's a temporal dead zone but that's a theory concept but what I'm saying
is that when you use let and const go through go through a process of read it as it is like
the first line if only if b is declared on the top then it will come but if when you are using
let and const it should like you should line by line like you should go from top to bottom
okay read it as it is that will help you to understand better like how would you actually
deal around with the let and const okay now if I considered that thing this should be also return
me an error right there is no b b is not defined itself when I'm trying to initialize here call it
right let's see this if this if it if it returns the same thing like cannot access a before
initialization
you see b is not defined it says
because this is coming after it is this clear guys how this is working
okay for this whenever you see let and const for me the symbol use case is that
I try to understand like what is our top line by line I try to understand the code and
fix it up only the problem comes with a var that's the reason we avoided var to write it down
everywhere that you see okay now one simple use case console dot log of c
now where c equal to one
one
what do you think
interesting
uh one thing again if I want to declare a variable in js how can I do it if I want to declare a
variable in js what is the syntax that I can use I have three things var let and const
let and const
isn't it am I using it here if I don't use this thing do you think the hosting works
hosting works with respect to type of variable isn't it
depends upon type of variable now even if I if you remember that we this used to work
like like this will work only in the use case where you like this is a simple use case right
what we have done is that I had declared it one but I have created a variable which will
be hoisted and then it will work but here I haven't created that variable itself I'm trying to
put it log for it okay this should also be returning a some error
you see c is not defined but if I try to console log again if I try to console log c again
it still says not defined let's say
let's say we say that
c equal to one and console dot log of c
this is working this way in a reverse because once a way when anything is declared that was like
I've told you that in non-stick environment this was supported but in strict environment this will
also break earlier we have seen this example where this was actually working reason behind
first when this is parsed when this actually values initialize this was considered as a variable
and the var keyword was added automatically and then we were able to access it but when
there is no var keyword hosting doesn't really happen for this one that's why we were getting
error for this use case and the way even if I write this this is working this wouldn't
work in a strict environment is this clear
yeah if we are not declaring a variable type by default it will take it as a var keyword
and post that you can use it but in strict environments when you use like
browser strict or node.js strict level environments it will throw you an error
okay I've enough if you use like this is a non-strict environment we haven't mentioned
anywhere use strict or anything so that's why it is working even if I re-declare c equal to one and
console log c but that doesn't really work it shouldn't be used that way okay
now just want to recheck guys this six questions I've covered let's say one one final question
before we take a break console.log of sum if I do this what do you think output should be
okay
not defined right
sum is not defined let's recheck this one
sum is not defined okay so I try to cover all the use cases which again covers up your hosting
concept and you know the topics that you have to revise it basic topics so hope the this seven
questions keeps you better understanding about things once we'll take a break for five minutes
we'll come back we'll have like I have still further 10 questions which will actually cover
one more concept that I actually want to introduce it I'll talk about that but we'll learn through
this examples itself building one by one okay really interesting topic guys come back in five
minutes where you will try to refresh your knowledge on this and we'll move ahead so five
minutes is fine right or else can I continue it depends on your thing like if you want a break
we can take a break or else if you want me to continue I can continue give me thumbs up for break
guys
okay let's take five minutes of break I'll start a five minutes timer we'll meet back in five minutes
you
uh guys is everyone back again
uh
okay uh give me thumbs up guys give me thumbs up if you are back
see it only one a few more would be really helpful
okay great so it was like going back to the question number seven
uh as it was not defined what if what if I add where sum here and I declare a function
a comma b and I try to return
a plus b
what it should be
does the answer need to change or answer will be still same
guys I'm waiting for your comment error might be now you need not to be might be use case
have enough so let's clear it up firstly uh is it a variable is it a variable which is storing
a function in it
let's just think in that perspective is it a variable which is showing a function in it
now oh first thing did I if I declare function this way then you can say that this was a function
but I declared a variable called sum isn't it so whenever I use where keyword and I declare
something it is mostly consider that where is always hoisted so we are talking about type of
data types right dive where is always hosted now even if you have function in it this where some
will be hoisted so it should be converting from not defined to undefined isn't it
going back from that concept wherever you see this keyword this culprit which will this will
work like in a hoisting concept and this will declare that where some it may not create that
function in it but it will declare it and that will be storing so this person actually irritated
many js developers so that's why we killed it we introduced let and const
okay but do you understand why this is undefined guys again let me try to re-show you this one
see this is coming as undefined that's that's what happens that's what happens when you build
a coding language in 10 days okay now there's another question a question related to this
concept itself let's say I have a console dot log I try to print total now
but see that how I'm talking how I'm introducing total now
still I'm returning that function itself so what do you think the output should be here
firstly think from hoisting concept itself whether the const total should be hoisted in global space
it shouldn't right it should not be like whenever I say that let and const go go as per reading I
said that hey console log total I am seeing anywhere total no it's below it's there below
but the variable is not var so it's a const I'll be getting something output here it will be
resulting in some error and that error is like you cannot use it before like total is not defined
or it doesn't exist you see that total is not defined
did you understand difference where a var really irritates people like in old age that's the reason
why people say that javascript is a headache that was headache was solved because this was a pill
which was solving our problem
guys did you understand this example difference between these two both seven and eight
seven and eight can we move it to next question
so question number nine let's see how many of you can answer this one this is interesting thing
let's say I try to console log and I say that some one of two comma three
and I have function some one and I return it a plus b what should be my output
whenever I declared about hoisting or talked about hoisting I talked about like two things get
hoisted variables and functions so once function is hoisted right I'll be able to access it I'll
be able to execute it isn't it so how if you if you guys think five give me thumbs up if you
if you guys think other the other way around give me thumbs down
right great guys I got once first time I got all people aligned with one answer
happy for that yeah it is five okay now let's take about some other example
question 10
okay let's have function called example one which is doesn't have anything in it
but I have one if condition which is all the ways true and when it is always all the ways true
I have var aa equal to one and let b be equal to two okay after that I'm trying to access them
both the things
now there is a one concept behind the scenes for this one but I just want to know like
how many of you think what should be the output for this one
one and undefined okay
one and not defined so I've received two answers how many of you if you guys agree
with Dheeraj answer give me thumbs up if you agree with Ashish answer give me thumb strong guys
guys please try to answer this one
okay one and one four people if your people are not able to think let me
know if you're not able to think anything okay we just executed the function then but
just want to know Ashish what's the reason behind you let's see let me show you first output
what generally happens when I execute this one
one if you see I got one and b is not defined so Ashish answer is right
Dheeraj you got it wrong here we'll explore the reason for that but Ashish do you know reason
or the person who's what what you can how
how can you say that it won't be available or not defined why do you think it that way
okay right so yeah firstly there's a one concept called let and const variables
are block scoped
have you heard this one have you heard the statement anytime
okay block scope now when to when we go for block when we go for block like if you if you cannot
if you cannot write
like logic in one line you go for block right if I say so example if let's say if I have this way
let's say if I have this way if true I can say where a equal to
one if there is only one thing I can write down this way but when I have multiple statements
when I have multiple statements I'm always opening two braces
whenever I'm opening a two braces whatever I write logic in it in between here whatever magic
happens here whatever magic happens here stays here with respect to let and const variables
whereas still where variables are hoisted in global space
is this clear guys this statement
like where and let are always block scope if there is a if you if you try to console log here
if you try to console log here you will be able to access bb but if you come out of this block
these two braces then you won't be able to access anything this and const which are coming inside
this block
okay
I hope this logic is clear why the output one and not defined is coming up
if there is anyone who didn't understand yet let me know
guys if you understood can you give me a thumbs up if you understand what is block scope and how
does it work for let and const whereas var is always hoisted it will come into the global
space and pollute it okay
so one strict suggestion would you ever use it a wire keyword in your project
it's just for learning guys it's just for learning js but never ever go to go to that keyword
never ever use that keyword where it's it's really bad if you use it in today's date okay
we are trying to understand how yeah like it created too many problems initially when I started
understanding out of college the repository I was working on was really 780 years old
and that happened five years back if you can imagine two years old code of js
first one month was like I literally had nightmare understanding concept literally
nightmares like var was such a I can say I mean it gives you goosebumps sometimes it behaves in
some way sometimes in different ways when you don't really understand js it's really difficult
okay
I revised this concept so that you will be able to figure it out yeah Ashish I completely like
because even I had that because I seen production bugs issues right how should we address them
now let's say I have var cc I created a variable called variable cc20 now let's
say I have a function example and inside this function I'm doing something is that true
and cc equal to one and not only this I'm creating it again and I'm trying to do console.log
cc also
so I'm calling an example
this one executed also I'm trying to do console.log cc
so I need output for this one a and output for b from here on game will be interesting guys
so people say sir one and one
okay
one and 20s guys if you think it's one and 20 give me thumbs up if you think one and one give me thumbs down
okay I've seen one and 20 people are four one and one are one but
let's let's see the exit let's see the output for this one I'll copy and I'll
give it to you show it to you like how this thing works okay and if you see I got an output of one
and 21st got an output of one and 21st but what I'll do it here is that what I'll do it here
in order to explain people who have got wrong right let me go to terminal
what just happened here let's see this one okay clear I'll put a debugger here
here here and even before the line starts
let's say I make it an example.js
okay I have to comment few things because all the not defines will result in error
okay I hope all things are clear but let's check this
okay where a equal to one where it is a equal to one
like if I try to execute this one a comment
and still have too many other let it be what I'll do is that in order to explain this
let's say firstly I'll write down answer here one and 20 so let me build
example one dot js
so that I can show you guys
let's say I have this example and I paste it here I have a debugger here itself
let's see what's happening here clearing it
and I try to execute this particular file okay now debugger is attached just see that
yeah use pad I didn't get your okay ipad okay just wanted to show real time so that I'm using
a debugging which is much better so the reason I'm doing this one is that even before the first
line of statement is executed let's see what things all are available here inside this globe this object
if you see inside this global object now let's say if I go to check this one firstly an example function
okay this is not coming inside this one but
let me see where this is loaded
this is working in node js part
this is file path and example
okay this is local scope whereas if I go for global scope
let's see this in browser itself guys that will be better easy
I'll create a index dot html
uh html5 let's say rdev
debugging
so I have a script
src
okay launch it
okay uh just a second we'll verify it here Kabir
if I go into sources I open this one I put a debugger here itself now once I refresh this one
now let's see what's actually happening here okay inside the global whenever this is done if you see
the cc is actually initialized as for the hoisting concept with undefined key also you will have an
example function which is present okay these two points are clear isn't it
now after that the next execution line would be eight right
do you guys agree the next execution line will be eight
now let's say if I go into eight what happens here now when this eight example is actually
executed it goes inside this if condition okay let's see if it goes inside this if condition
it is whenever I create a new variable it is created inside its particular scope
this particular scope is this clear firstly this variable got created
not inside the global scope it created inside the local scope inside this if you see it also has
a window object coming along with it now this window object also has cc but we are not using
that parent one we are using its custom inside its scope is this clear like why the we are not
updating the outer one which is why because the reason outer one still be 20 we have redeclared
that one a new one in its local scope I hope now what is this is called here
what is this is called here for this condition for all this for this example itself
what this is called here this is something called is called as lexical environment have you heard
this keyword lexical environment okay so lexical environment let's open this
lexical environment in javascript
let me open any medium
if you see
what it is saying lexical environment in the javascript is a data structure
yeah if what it is talking about that stores the variable and function that are defined in the
current scope and all of the outer scopes okay it is also known as lexical scope now whenever we say
that lexical scope what is exactly meant is that this current cc plus parent scope now the parent
scope for this one this particular function is a global scope isn't it so the lexical environment
whenever we say that lexical environment the current local scope plus it's all parent scopes
combined together is called a lexical environment that is what a lexical scope is called as
is it this point here just one definition that the current scope and all the outer scopes combined
is called as a lexical environment because if you see it here the example what they gave okay
global execution context is having a var a equal to one and execution context one when
when they're executing function one they have var a equal to two okay now
if i have this further example i can show but i'll give you four more example better examples
to understand this one but the basic definition is this one itself is the current scope plus all
the outer scopes combined together is called as a lexical environment okay if i have other definitions
if you see uh this definition also lexical environment in a javascript is simple object
consisting of two parts a reference to the outer environment and the environment record the current
environment record the current environment record is always present in local scope and this is
pointing to an outer environment is it clear this point is clear
one final thumbs up guys like if this point is clear that you got understanding of what lexical
environment is okay and why the 1920 output is coming because this is not being changed which
is in global environment a local scope is created inside that only the value is updated
okay now if this point is clear let's go back to the questions uh question number 12
this is another interesting questions from now on we'll see how many of you can think of this one
let's say where dd i have 20 initialized here and let's have a function called example two
and inside this example two what i'll do is that i'll say that if true dd equal to one
also i'll do something like console dot log dd let's say this is one and i execute this example
two and also i console dot log dd which is p here so what should be output guys for this use case
for this use case
everyone says one and one is there any other answer guys like if you think uh it should be
one and twenty muneshwara says one and twenty uh one final check if you believe one and one
give me thumbs up if you think one and 20s are right answer give me thumbs down
okay i see two people three people three versus three
okay now
uh let's say what what would be answer let's say debug and see it directly i
it should be both one and one actually why it should be one and one firstly i'll talk about
that before that i'll execute it here and word to you you see one and one the reason why it is
one and one i'll talk about that okay re-executing this okay first line number dd is initialized
in global scope you'll have dd but if i go to line number eight where i'm executing function two
if i see in the global scope i'll have dd 20 initialized but once i go into a separate
execution context when separate execution context is created uh from execution if you
remember execution context we made uh we create a new scope the local scope is there here in the
local scope if you see i'm having this here here i'm not recreating value here but i'm having a
attachment reference like when you say that lexical environment the lexical environment
is current environment plus its parent environment uh here you have dd you are you are making an
update to this dd let's say if i go to this line you update a dd now inside this if you see you
made a dd updated one now this one is actually pointing to which one is it to global scope itself
like dd one inside the global is also in each updated is this point clear how that
one is actually updating the global scope logic so here when we refer again to refer this dd we
have still global scope itself which is a lexical scope it prints one then again here it's still
we are having one so is this clear guys why one and one people who gave me thumbs down for one
and twenty muneshwara pramod abhinav okay i got two thumb two thumbs up uh abhinav
did you got this point
okay cool now once this is clear let's go for another example
uh i'm not able to scroll system hanged or what okay i'll remove the debuggers
let's say i go for 13 example in this example number 13 let's say i
make something i build some function let's say i have a function called parent
let's say i also have a declared a variable called a equal to 20 then also think like i
have a child function in it what i'm trying to do is i'm trying to do a console dot log here of a
and i execute child here
here plus i execute parent outside here
okay so what do you think the output should be here for this a
what will a point do
uh 20 guys do you agree with 20
uh no one is acting anything no one is saying anything uh abhinav says no dira says 20
muneshwara says 20 so abhinav what what you're you're saying undefined right okay uh
rajini is saying 20 so firstly uh let's say what uh can you say lexical environment lexical
scope for this one what could be lexical scope for this one current scope plus parent scope
so
it reaches global scope
okay
let's i cut this from here
here
i cut it i paste it here
i hope you got the point like what is lexical scope here if you see
in my current scope do i have a in my current scope do i have a when i'm executing this child
do i have in my current scope does value a is available variable a is available no but when i
go and see it in my parent does a is available in my parent does a is available so i'll be should be
able to print 20 here isn't it once it is available it shouldn't be undefined or not defined anything
anything right let's see this let's see this if we are getting this output
if you see i'm getting a 20 output uh do i need to debug and show is show this guys because
this is pretty straightforward example isn't it just now we understood lexical scope using
two examples i hope abhinav you your doubt is also resolved did you get this point
okay great now then there is another interesting question guys
question number 14 from now on it would be much trickier i would give enough time
for you to think of it okay so just understand complete question guys before you know answering
anything
let's say i have a parent i have a var so wherever you see a var you have to think
slowly okay if later in const it's pretty straightforward i have child
inside child i'll try to console dot log a again i have function child two inside it
inside child two i console dot log a okay now here i try to call
let's say i don't call child to here but i call child to here
and i try to execute parent one what do you think my output should be
for this one
a and this one b ashi says error how many of you think it should be returning an error
abhinav says here any reason guys why do you say that it should be an error
okay muneeshwara says 20 and not defined
because we call child to after child right so firstly this should be resulting an error guys
if you think why is that i don't if i collapse this one i don't have child to execute anywhere
here first in the scope okay parent is available by default to the child but child elements are
not available to parent it's a children child child who is inside a child if we execute child
here then we might get some output but other cases i should be getting an error is this clear
why this should be actually coming out returning an error let's see if this is happening it
if you see child two is not defined but if i convert this into child one
if i convert this into child let's say what should be my output
what should be my output still only 20
okay do you think b should be printing or b shouldn't be throwing an error itself
we are not even executing this function guys so b won't be outputting anything isn't it only 20
i hope that is making sense because we are not executing this part
only if i call this one then the both the outputs will be 20 and 20
isn't it when i execute all the things it will go for the pair
its whole lexical scope in the lexical scope the value of a is equal into 20
and then i'll be able to print 20 and 20 okay with one example i try to replicate three scenarios
because here comes a new question
okay let's say
a function i call it as parent two
inside this parent function i have again where a equal to 20
inside this function where let's say i have a child inside this channel i'll try to console.log
a after console.logging a i'll try to build a child to inside this child too i'll try to console.log
a okay but but when i'm trying to console.log child to here i initialized where a equal
to 10 and i call child to then i executed child here and i called parent to here
what do you think output should be for a and b
ashish says 10 and 20
20 and 10 corrected yourself very fast
guys take your time i need few of answers zeerat says 10 and 10 yeah ashish take your time take
your time muneshwara says 20 and 10
if you go from lexical scoping point of you right like think one function is created then
there is a another execution context created it has a own scope and its parent scope
divide it that way if a value is available in current scope it don't it won't even reach out
to the parent scope only if not available then it will go up
frankly frankly if i would say i didn't receive a right answer yet
anyone no one has given me right answer
no one has given me right answer all the combinations were wrong just think of it
guys where things are going to just imagine from execution context point of view hoisting point
of view because here i have told you that there is a one person sitting that person is like you
know the var keyword really create a tabl
can anyone think of it if not i will talk about it
okay let's let's go step by step guys let's go step by step this function is there
okay this function is there this will not be called unless this line is executed isn't it
this function once we call this function this line will be executed this whole function once
we go inside this function i see that it it has a memory certain memory coming from the global
scope and its current scope in the current scope value a 20 is available and the child function
is you know declared initialized but not yet executed called then i'm calling it here
once i'm calling it i am going inside it here then i see a separate execution context for
each function as it is created i see there is a var is available when i see a variable with var
that is hoisted when it is hoisted what is our default value assigned to the value which is hoisted
default value muneshwara this line is not yet executed we are still here at the line
execution of 124 it would be undefined right guys are you able to relate like
this value is actually it's it's in its current scope they say it's it's made this block it's in
current scope in that scope a new value is created whenever we saw we just saw that on above
simple examples var examples that always get var get hoisted and initial value is undefined
so what should be the value of a here what should be the value of a here
undefined right okay guys is this clear to everyone why we are getting undefined here first
everyone is there anyone who didn't understand this point
is there anyone who didn't understand this point rechecking with you all
guys is there anyone who didn't understand this point
okay i'll take it as no then once this is executed this line will be executed then in our local scope
in this current scope of child value is updated a equal to 10 then child two is called once this
is called i'm trying to execute it here in the current scope it doesn't have so it will go to
its parent scope which is of child scope what is the value of value of a child scope
it is 10 so the value should be undefined and 10
so are you able to relate this guys
this might of questions might be asked in your contest you see undefined and 10 is coming out
okay do you want another further questions on this like i can create more complicated questions
want to practice more
because i just introduce only var variables what if i combine with let
right it will create my further confusion
there can be multiple uh you know if i take one more example just think of this thing i have two
questions left with me which i prepared it so that you will be all uh clear with the concepts
now if you see this example guys see this example take your time take the amount of time that you
need i am here if you need one hour also that's fine we will understand this one and leave it
because uh this place are tricky where we people fail to understand things how execution context
lexical scoping hoisting three things are working together it builds so much amount of knowledge
over the classes that we are able to at least relate them things will come with practice but
able to at least relate them things will come with practice but just think of it what could
be an expected answer for this one go step by step
how i it happened with me when i was learning concepts but i that's the reason why i'm putting
all the examples in one file so that you go through it you revise once in a short
huh execution context hoisting and uh you know uh lexical scope everything is one short may
a key file may everything will be clear all the concepts so just think of this guys what
will be the output for a and b and c part
so
okay uh ashi says 20 then he says undefined right then he says 10
okay
okay then he says 10
okay then 20
as you had two answers promotes answer and ashi's answer
uh anyone else who's trying out figuring out answer for this one
let's let's solve this case let's solve this let's figure out now muneshwara says undefined
10 and 20 okay no no worries case let's let's break down again step by step
let's break down step by step i called parent three he called parent three uh in its scope
uh in its scope value is there child function is declared and called once i'm going inside
this child function i see a console log a but before it start executing we know that memory
execution phase happens and uh it checks if there is any new variables and functions are declared
we see that it is uh child who is declared it will be hoisted but there is no other extra
variables are uh you know declared so directly it it sees that okay value a variable a is not
available in current scope it will go and check for the parent scope it says that hey in parent
scope 20 is available so from the lexical scope of parent it will get 20 okay then i see that hey
i am updating value of a equal to 10 now this value of 10 should be actually updated here
which is parent scope because a variable is declared in the parent scope isn't it till here
it's clear guys till here it's clear what just happened where how we updated 20 equal to 10
then we went on to call a child function inside child once a separate execution context is created
memory uh creation phase happens and function variables are hoisted now i see that hey where
a is hoisted and set to undefined now i'm trying to access a which is undefined not yet
dick uh initialized isn't it so i get here undefined
now how i'm able to solve how i'm able to solve is i'm actually trying to read it through step
by step it will help you whenever you are attempting this because it's on my screen on
my laptop i'm able to drop close the functions and read it through but whenever you get these
use cases read it through one by one separate execution context hoisting memory execution then
code execution okay now once child two is closed now i come back i this part is done then this part
is done then i try to access console log of a if this value is already updated by 10
so i'll get 20 undefined and 10
is this clear guys
dhiraj you just called it out 20 undefined and 20 okay now let's see this if if my answer is right
okay you see 20 undefined and 10 okay great guys people who are able to guess it kudos to them
one final example uh okay for this part
let's say the question number 17
this question
here comes a combination with let guys
now you not not even need to think from perspective of execution context memory
creation you want to have to think in terms of scopes
context memory creation you want to have to think in terms of scopes
okay i have four outputs now in this this is further actually complicated one
but i hope a few people at least get it right
or even out of four options if you get a good amount of things right that's also cool
okay
oh just one change
one change other things are right
think of it again
why did you call an undefined check undefined that firstly
if a variable is not available in local context it checks parents lexical scope what if I'm
updating some parent value now updating a parent value it's logical right I can do it or if I'm
trying to print it I should be able to get it from a parent and Ashish for you you have
to check the last one anyone else trying it guys anyone else trying it right so I got
one right answer but let's explore this guys again step by step firstly going back executing
this one to cross checking if you see it's triple 10 and 20 firstly Pramod has answered right Pramod
has sent me personally kudos Pramod but we'll come back to this one okay we'll see why this
has actually worked and why not okay I'll minimize everything firstly parent fold 4 is
called variable a 20 is initialized I go inside the child here I see when I host things nothing
is with aware so I have to read it as it is later equal to 10 I got a console log of a I
print 10 here okay then I went into the child too okay and I seen console log of a okay I
don't have a value available here a well is not available so I'll update it value I mean I'll
get it from a parent scope lexical scope which is this one then then I'm updating a equal to
30 now let's say a equal to 30 which value will be should be actually updated this one of this
one Ashish when I do this a equal to 30 here at line number 160 immediate parent right which
is this one you know now if it is so if it is so let's see this let's see if I am updating
this immediate parent and I come out of that one here I should be getting an output as output
should be 30 here right if the immediate parent is outputted immediate parent is updated actually
then if I come out if I come out by default firstly here it should be 20 itself but now
let's see what actually happened here what actually happened here okay what why this a
equal to 30 didn't apply when I updated I mean executed the same piece of code okay I'll show
you guys here in the debugger mode I'll copy that that's the reason why when I told that I'll
introduce later in const it will change a bit okay this is the expected thing but the output
surprising was 10 here printing before calling child to hmm right yeah sorry pardon me yeah
it was called before thanks Munesh for a pointed out so did you guys see this that I even got
confused but the child was called later on and it updated this let later then we got 11 and 20
but kudos to promote promote got it right and there's one more example guys last one example
then we'll end the session today we'll come to will introduce closures in the next class
just think of this thing guys I have again four things there's a one change that I have done it
here I think I asked his answer you can actually copy paste your answer I guess think of it
right this is the answer that we were expecting earlier but it was here at 10
but only the changing the way we called got changed so it should be 10 again 10 here since
it got updated we should be value should be updated as 30 then this is actually getting
from the large parent scope complete scope so it should be 20 I hope this is clear to everyone
guys I hope you got you had fun thinking about execution context harvesting concept mixing them
I prefer question yeah got it even I didn't think at that moment even I got confused but
it's okay once you go through step by step and read it properly guys you'll be able to figure
but guys had you had fun revising this concepts how was it it was good like going through this
questions and refreshing all the things that concepts that we have gone through and explored
it so next class next class mostly will be based on this knowledge where you have to have a
understanding on scopes understanding on hoisting with respect to where keywords and let and const
and how this lexically you know we are able to access the parent variables once those things
are clear we'll start something called as a closure if I say what is enclosure if it would
be like 90% we have already covered only some part of his remaining which I'll cover it in
next class I don't want to push it further today because we have covered good amount of
content today okay so we have one major topic two things once one thing I'll prefer to help you
out learn it like one I want to teach you guys is something called as currying functions function
currying this is which is again of curriculum I'll try to put it in same set of examples where
we have it then you will have this one closures will spend one class completely on closures okay
these two topics will cover in next class then we'll have one final class where I'll try to
spend one hour on the content then I'll give you enough amount of time to revise go through
the whole notes of get up what we have learned it if you have doubts I'd be it will be like a long
session where I can be you can we can sit together discuss any topic related to JS from execution
context to event loop all synchronous asynchronous codes event handling the projects we have discussed
all the array methods polyfills too much of content was covered guys I know it is really
huge but I'll be here where we can spend one hour of time going through all the notes and
figuring out everything trying to see remember all the things right on the next Thursday class
but before that I just want you to go through these examples and come back we'll spend some
good amount of time understanding closures because that's also one of the concept which
is beautiful concepts one of the beautiful concept I would say that where people struggle to
understand it okay this is the reason why I've took more than around 18 19 20 examples breaking
down one example into multiple parts to understand and you know make yourself pressed up with these
things and then we'll go to that topic okay guys so with this I'll start the doubt session guys I'll
push the code if you have any doubts we can still hang in around if it is related to call
bind apply polyfills or anything I'll still sit here and we can discuss further okay I'm
going to start the doubt session okay let me push the code sorry
so we have you know catered 30 classes for building all the basics of HTML CSS and JS
where it is an intense amount of knowledge I completely agree that to carry on all the
things one so if someone is starting from beginner but I hope you got to learn this
one thank you Ashish okay so revise those projects revise those all the events how do
you handle events and everything right because what I'm worried much about is that from my
previous experience people struggle whenever I talk about this one right mock interviews
they they try to think like what topic should I prepare well what topic shouldn't I prepare
well so if you see that asynchronous JS we have covered it much in detail and that will
be much more focused from the mock interview perspective like what are promises what is
async await how you make a series calls how we make parallel calls how we make an API call how
things works in event loop what is an execution context how things are actually passed why var
variable is such a thing why we all the developers hate it right too many things going on but I try
to make it as easy as much possible for you to understand it and ready open forum in order to
like if you have it any questions happy to be here and discuss it right anything you have it do
let me know guys open for understanding and discussing it I'll wait for two three minutes
in case you have doubts or else will close the session most of the I mean things right all these
things that we are learning are like for our basic building blocks for our react because if
you go in today's era this all things will help you to build your basics and clear interviews per
se but this understanding this one will make your journey of learning react will be further easy
so this is for from interview perspective this is important but few people I know is that someone
have started journey in reverse they pick it up what is more important in industry react let's
start learning react and from there they come back to HTML, CSS and JS but the way we are learning
it's I believe this curriculum is really designed in a way that we cover whole topics and you know
sit together I my idea is that since I'm covering beginner there are people who don't even know
anything for them it is difficult at one shot to get it everything so I ask them like it's a six
month journey where I'll cover the whole web try to put in hours where we'll cover the whole web
part and you'll completely love it and remember that that I've shared you a block yeah I've shared
you a block where how things run behind the scenes combining HTML, CSS, JS hope you go
through it read through it and in case you have anything doubt with that we are I'm here you can
ping me in whatsapp chat I'll do that but let's let's read it through let's build that knowledge
and when you face when you get a call interview call right we shouldn't be like that I don't know
this or don't understand or not confident on that I'm trying to give my all of us you should
be getting from your efforts guys so Muneshwar I hope you are learning lot you are getting concepts
cleared like all things I've seen you one of the consistent person who attends classes okay so I
hope your PSP percentages are also high and you've been maintaining things right so keep
doing that guys keep your PSPs high and keep learning things yeah sure sure Ashish like
there are too many people who help help can help us and even like you know you have a big
community the main advantage of scaler is the community you have many people in your batch
itself are experienced professional you being fresher they many people can refer you like you
pick you talk to 10 20 people 10 20 people are working in different talks if you are confident
with your knowledge reach out them if even 10 people refer you even if you get three calls
convert one out of three so 20 odd people reach out 10 people referral three calls convert one
the job is set if not scalar placements are anyways there if you keep your PSPs and everything
and with that thank you Ashish with this I'll end the session guys I don't say doubts it's
me continuously speaking so hope you have a great weekend and learning time again a special
request is just go through it go through the things I'll update this readme file which class
is covering which concepts I've written till class 20 I have to cover eight classes content
which will I'll update it just now and then I'll push it so that you can see a topic and go to
that particular class and read it through okay so guys then with that good night take
care see you on Tuesday good night guys bye bye